Guide to the Mary Augusta Scott Papers, approximately 1870-1917
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Mary Augusta Scott Papers
approximately 1870-1917
Scott, Mary Augusta, 1851-1918
8.5 cubic feet (10 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Correspondence, manuscripts, printed material, journals and photographs relating to Scott's personal life and professional life as an author and professor of English at Smith College.
Biographical Note
Mary Augusta Scott (1851-1918), born in Dayton, OH, was one of a generation of early Vassar graduates who embraced and exemplified the scholarly life. A member of the class of 1876, she also received a master's degree from Vassar College. Miss Scott studied at Newnham College, Cambridge University, and at Johns Hopkins; but she was particularly proud to have been the first woman fellow at Yale, where she earned her Ph.D. in 1894.
A professor of English at Smith from 1902, Miss Scott worked hard for her students, particularly those who showed promise. Intensely private, she was regarded as a somewhat mysterious and glamorous figure on campus. Although she edited and published The Essays of Francis Bacon, her most notable scholarly work was Elizabethan Translations from the Italian, published in the Vassar Semi-Centennial Series. She was a frequent contributor to The Dial and other literary and academic journals.
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, diaries, manuscripts, programs, clippings, course materials, research notes, notebooks, reports, photographs, and other materials relating to her personal and professional life. Correspondents include Elizabeth Blackwell, Anne Jemima Clough, Lewis Einstein, Horace Howard Furness, Dr. Howard Atwood Kelly, Alice M. Longfellow, Joseph K. Murray, Agnes Repplier, Eleanor Sedgwick, Henry Dwight Sedgwick, and the Underhill family (England). Subjects in the correspondence include her academic positions, dispute with Einstein over her allegations that he appropriated her research, her publications, the education of women, and family affairs. Correspondence with Dr. Kelly concerns her health, religious views, their working partnership, intellectual discussions, the capabilities of women, her problems supporting herself, her desire for a home, and comments on Bryn Mawr. Her diaries, 1882-1906, discuss her reading, visits to Vassar College by Julia Ward Howe, Lyman Abbott, and other lecturers, social events, plays seen, ideas, and comments on writers. There are also reports, course materials, class records, and correspondence with students from Smith College, 1902-1912; and her manuscripts, notes, galleys of her published works, and articles by others on women's education in England and America and on literary topics, 1885-1916. Collection includes typescript copies of her diaries and of her correspondence with Dr. Kelly.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Blackwell, Elizabeth, 1821-1910; Clough, Anne Jemima; Einstein, Lewis, 1877-1967; Furness, Horace Howard, 1833-1912; Kelly, Howard A. (Howard Atwood), 1858-1943; Longfellow, Alice M. (Alice Mary), 1850-1928; Murray, Joseph K.; Repplier, Agnes, 1855-1950; Sedgwick, Eleanor; Sedgwick, Henry Dwight, 1861-1957; Howe, Julia Ward, 1819-1910; Abbott, Lyman, 1835-1922; Underhill family
Organizations:
Vassar College; Newnham College; Smith College--Faculty; Smith College--Students; Yale University--Students; Bryn Mawr College
Subjects:
Women--Diaries; Women's colleges--Massachusetts--Northampton; Women's colleges--Pennsylvania--Bryn Mawr; English language--Study and teaching; Literature publishing; Literature--Women authors; Women--Education--England; Women--Education; Books and reading; Theater; Authors; Plagiarism; Women college teachers; Women authors, American
Document Types:
Diaries; Photographs
VCL Categories
Education; Literature and Writing
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, July 2008.
Acquisition Information
Estate of Mary Augusta Scott.
Series List
- Series I. Biographical Information, Education, And Professional Career
- Series II. Organizations and Subject Files
- Series III. Writings
- Series IV. Correspondence
Container List
- Series I: Biographical Information, Education, And Professional Career
  - Biographical information (Folder 2.1)
  - Journal, 1882-1906 (Folder 2.2)
  - Typed transcript of 1882-1906 journal (Folder 2.3)
  - Journal, July 1882 (Box 1)
  - Travel journal, July-Aug 1886 (Box 1)
  - Travel journal, Sep-Oct 1886 (Box 1)
  - Travel journal, Oct 1886 - Jan 1887 (Box 1)
  - Travel journal, Jan - Feb 1887 (Box 1)
  - Travel journal, July 1887- Feb 1888 (Box 1)
  - Notebook — "Good Stories (Box 1)
  - Notebook — "Foreign Addresses" (Box 1)
  - Notebooks — Finances (6 volumes) (Box 1)
  - Personal finances and miscellaneous business (Folder 2.4)
  - Codicil to Will of M.A. Scott (Folder 2.5)
  - Photographs (Folder 2.6)
  - Letters of recommendation (Folder 8.1)
  - Public schools, Washington, D.C. (Folder 8.2)
  - Public schools, Washington, D.C. — Letters from J. Ormand Wilson, Superintendent of Schools, 1870-1888 (Folder 2.7)
  - Vassar College (Folder 2.8)
  - Sauveur College of Languages, 1885 (Folder 2.9)
  - Packer Institute, 1884-1888 (Folders 8.3 - 8.4)
  - Packer Institute — See also, Correspondence —Backus
  - Bryn Mawr School. (Folder 2.10)
  - University of Illinois, Columbia University, Barnard, and other schools — correspondence regarding positions, 1889-1902? (Folder 2.11)
  - Cambridge University — Includes a manuscript by Scott, "Women at the University of Cambridge" (Folder 2.12)
  - Cambridge University — Newnham College (Folder 2.13)
  - Cambridge University — Letters from Annie Jemima Cough and B. A. Clough, photographs, programs, and notes, 1886-1898 (Folder 2.14)
  - Cambridge University — Letters from Eleanor Sedgwick, 1895-1909 (Folder 2.15)
  - Cambridge University — Letters from, and material about, Henry Sedgwick, 1884-1895 (Folder 2.16)
  - Cambridge University — Papers written at Cambridge, 1886-1887 (Folders 8.5 - 8.6)
  - Standard Dictionary work, Funk and Wagnalls, 1891-1892 (Folder 2.17)
  - Yale University — Correspondence and clippings about fellowship awarded M.A.S., 1892-1910 (Folders 2.18 - 2.19)
  - Yale University — Ph.D. diploma, 1894 (Box 10)
  - Smith College — Letters of appointment, 1902 (Folder 2.20)
  - Smith College — Correspondence with Presidents L. Clark Seelye and M. J. Burton (Folder 2.21)
  - Smith College — Graduate work (Folder 2.22)
  - Smith College — Correspondence regarding sabbaticals (Folder 2.23)
  - Smith College — Correspondence from students (Folder 2.24)
  - Smith College — Myrtle Mann, 1912 (Folder 2.25)
  - Smith College — Methods of appointment (Folder 2.26)
  - Smith College — Honors courses (Folder 2.27)
  - Smith College — Curriculum revision (Folder 2.28)
  - Smith College — English Department — Includes correspondence and reports (Folders 8.7 - 8.8)
  - Smith College — English examinations (Folder 8.9)
  - Smith College — Marking systems (Folder 8.10)
  - "Bertha’s exercises for my voice, 1892-1893" (Folder 2.29)
  - The Flexner Report at Johns Hopkins University. Includes letters from Dr. Howard A. Kelly, 1911 (Folder 2.30)
  - Controversy regarding President Frederick H. Sykes of Connecticut College, 1916-1917 (Folder 2.31)
  - Grant application to Carnegie Institution, 1903 (Folder 2.32)
  - Miscellaneous notebooks — includes school and college notes, research notes, and grade books (Box 4)
- Series II: Organizations and Subject Files
  - American Association of University Professors (Folder 2.33)
  - Brooklyn Ethical Association (Folder 2.34)
  - Dante Society (Folder 2.35)
  - Modern Language Association (Folder 2.36)
  - Miscellaneous organizations, including the Atlantic Union and the American Federation of Arts (Folder 2.37)
  - Relations with libraries (Folder 2.38)
  - Learned women — Manuscripts, notes, clippings, and publications (Folder 2.39)
  - Isabella d’Este — Notes and clippings. (Folder 2.40)
  - Dr. Elizabeth Blackwell and women in the medical profession (Folder 2.41)
  - Admission of women to law school (Folder 2.42)
  - Coeducation — Notes by M.A.S. for a letter written to a Barnard College trustee (Folder 2.43)
  - Women's colleges and education (Folders 2.44 - 2.45)
  - Thomas Frederick Crane (Folder 2.46)
  - Impeachment of Andrew Johnson, (1 ticket) (Folder 3.24)
- Series III: Writings
  - List of papers written between 1882-1913 (Folder 7.1)
  - Letters to journals (Folder 7.2)
  - Ballads — Notes and published items (Folders 7.3 - 7.4)
  - "The Book of the Courtyer" " (Modern Language Association of America, 1901) — Notes and manuscript of published article. (Folders 7.5 - 7.6)
  - "The Book of the Courtyer" — Correspondence (Folder 6.59)
  - Chaucer — Notes and manuscript, 1885 (Folder 7.7 - 7.8)
  - "Dante’s Political Opinions" — Manuscript (1893), notes, and a letter of criticism by Kenneth McKenzie (Folder 7.9)
  - "De Quincey" — Manuscript and typed copy of a paper read at Smith College, 23 Feb 1892 (Folder 7.10)
  - "Dr. Jedway’s Phantasm" — Manuscripts and notes (Folder 7.11)
  - "A Double Hallucination: A True Story" (Folder 7.12)
  - Galateo. Bibliography and notes. (Folder 7.13)
  - "The Growth of Language" — Manuscript and typed copy of a paper read before the Brooklyn Ethical Society,., 10 Feb 1889 (Folder 7.14)
  - "The Italian Novella" — Notes and manuscript of a paper read at Yale University, 28 Dec 1895 (Folder 7.15)
  - The Italian Renaissance in England — Notes (Folder 7.16)
  - Italian travelers — Notes (Folder 7.17)
  - Italianated plays — Notes (Folder 7.18)
  - "Kant’s refutation of idealism" — Notes (Folder 7.19)
  - "Luxury" — Manuscript (Folder 7.20)
  - Montaigne — Notes (Folder 7.21)
  - "Newstead Abbey" — Manuscript (Folder 7.22)
  - Notes for Modern Language Notes, The Nation, etc. (Folder 7.23)
  - "Objectification of the Will" — Manuscript, 1892 (Folder 7.24)
  - "The Old English People, Traits, Speech, Spirit" — Manuscript, 1885 (Folder 7.25)
  - Philosophy lecture notes (Folder 7.26)
  - "Puritanism and the Stage" — Manuscript and typescript, 1894 (Folder 7.27)
  - "Queen Elizabeth’s Signature" — 2 versions of manuscript. (Folder 7.28)
  - Romance in Prose — Manuscript (Folder 7.29)
  - Scottish vernacular literature — Notes and clippings (Folder 7.30)
  - Shakespeare in Elizabethan translations — Notes, published items, and clippings (Folder 7.31)
  - Shelly — Notes on a lecture by Edmund Gosse, 1886 (Folder 7.32)
  - "Short True Stories" — Manuscripts and clippings (Folder 7.33)
  - "Yvain, le Chevalier au Lio" — Manuscript, 1893 (Folder 7.34)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Folder 7.35)
  - Copies of some published articles and letters (Folder 7.36)
  - Old Salem in its Habit as it Lived (Folder 3.1)
  - Ballads and Songs of the United States (published Vassar Quarterly?) (Folder 3.2)
  - Alice Spencer, Countess of Derby, and English Poetry: a Great Lady and a Great Tradition (published in The Dial, 1913) (Folder 3.3)
  - Powlert: a folk-song word that is not in the new English Dictionary (Folder 3.4)
  - The Essays of Francis Bacon — Manuscript, galleys, bibliography, correspondence, and royalty reports (Folders 3.5 - 3.15)
  - The Essays of Francis Bacon — Galleys (Folders 8.11 - 8.12)
  - The Essays of Francis Bacon — Correspondence (Folder 6.58)
  - Elizabethan Translations from the Italian — Transcripts of Correspondence (Folder 3.16)
  - Elizabethan Translations from the Italian — Correspondence (Folders 6.60 - 6.68)
  - Elizabethan Translations from the Italian — Correspondence relating to dispute with Lewis Einstein, 1903-1911 (Folders 6.69 - 6.77)
  - Elizabethan Translations from the Italian — Einstein clippings (Folder 3.17)
  - Elizabethan Translations from the Italian — Einstein publications (Folder 3.18)
  - Elizabethan Translations from the Italian — Scott's reviews of Einstein's Italian Renaissance, 1903 (Folder 3.19)
  - Elizabethan Translations from the Italian — Scott's annotated copy of Einstein's Italian Renaissance (Box 1)
  - Elizabethan Translations from the Italian — Notes on Einstein's Italian Renaissance— (Folder 8.13)
  - Elizabethan Translations from the Italian — Notices and reviews (Folder 8.14)
  - Elizabethan Translations from the Italian — Certificate of copyright (Folder 3.20)
  - Elizabethan Translations from the Italian — Notes (Folder 3.21)
  - Elizabethan Translations from the Italian — Notebooks (Folder 3.22)
  - Elizabethan Translations from the Italian — Notebooks — Index (Folder 3.23)
  - Elizabethan Translations from the Italian — Drafts and galleys (Box 9)
  - Elizabethan Translations from the Italian — Galleys (Box 10)
  - Tragicomedy notes (Box 3)
- Series IV. Correspondence
  - Abbatt, William, 1907-1916 (Folder 5.1)
  - Backus, Truman J., 1880-1884 (Folder 5.2)
  - Backus, Truman J. — See also Packer Institute, Box 1
  - Browne, Francis F. and Waldo R., 1889-1916 (Folders 5.3 - 5.6)
  - Carman, Mary L., 1887-1896 (Folder 5.7)
  - Cayley, Mary, 1888-1896 (Folder 5.8)
  - Clark, Amelia, 1902 (Folder 6.13)
  - Collins, Charles, 1886-1911 (Folders 5.9 - 5.10)
  - Furness, Horace Howard, 1895-1915 (Folders 5.11 - 5.12)
  - Gardiner, H. N., 1885-1897 (Folders 5.13 - 5.15)
  - Geddes, James Jr., 1902-1915 (Folders 5.16 - 5.18)
  - Johnston, Dr. William W., 1887-1902 (Folders 5.19 - 5.21)
  - Jordan, Mary A., 1881-1897 (Folders 5.22 - 5.23)
  - Jusserand, Jean Jules, 1900-1916 (Folder 5.24)
  - Kelly, Howard A. — incoming, 1893-1917 (Folders 5.25 - 5.41)
  - Kelly, Howard A. — outgoing, 1894-1895 (Folder 5.42)
  - Kelly, Howard A.— typed transcripts of selected incoming (Folder 2.47)
  - Kelly, Howard A. — typed transcripts of outgoing (Folder 2.48)
  - Kelly, Howard A. — Biographical material (Folder 5.43)
  - Kelly, Howard A. — Photographs (Folder 5.44)
  - Kelly, Howard A. — Clippings (Folder 5.45)
  - Kelly, Howard A. — Publications (Folder 5.46)
  - Kelly, Howard A. — Publications (Box 10)
  - Kelly, Howard A. — Lord's Day posters (Box 10)
  - Kelly, Howard A. — Miscellaneous (Folder 5.47)
  - Kennedy, John W., 1902-1916 (Folders 6.1 - 6.2)
  - Knapp, C. S., 1902 (Folder 6.14)
  - Lounesbury, F. R., 1893-1908 (Folders 6.3 - 6.5)
  - Miller, Dewitt (from and about), 1909-1911 (Folder 6.6)
  - Mower, Annie Penfield, 1882-1898 (Folder 6.7)
  - Murray, Joseph K., 1897-1905 (Folder 6.8-6.10)
  - Murray, Harold G., 1905 (Folder 6.11)
  - Nichols, Martha, 1909-1914 (Folder 6.15)
  - Opdycke, L. E., 1902-1908 (Folders 6.16 - 6.17)
  - "Mr. Tracy,", 1900 (Folder 6.12)
  - "Mr. Tracy" — see also 2 letters in V.C. Autograph File
  - Underhill, Annie, G.E., and H.J, 1887-1892 (Folder 6.18)
  - Underhill, H.M., 1888-1914 (Folders 6.19 - 6.21)
  - Underhill, Maud, 1888-1912 (Folders 6.22 - 6.26)
  - White, Alain C., 1900-1917 (Folder 6.27)
  - Wilson, C. W., 1887-1912, n.d. (Folders 6.28 - 6.35)
  - Wilson, Edith, 1888-1890 (Folder 6.36)
  - Wilson, Katherine K., 1888-1912 (Folders 6.37 - 6.40)
  - Wilson, R. K., 1887-1917 (Folders 6.41 - 6.44)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, A-B (Folder 6.45)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, C (Folder 6.46)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, D-E (Folder 6.47)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, F (Folder 6.48)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, G-H (Folder 6.49)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, K-L (Folder 6.50)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, M (Folder 6.51)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, N-P (Folder 6.52)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, Q-R (Folder 6.53)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, S (Folder 6.54)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, T (Folder 6.55)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, W (Folder 6.56)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, unidentified (Folder 6.57)